<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A catechisme in briefe questions and answers containing such things as are to be known or had by all such as would partake the sacrament of the Lords Supper with comfort / by John Geree ...</title>
            <author>Geree, John, 1601?-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G588</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43196</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">26981562</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 26981562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109900</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42650)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109900)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1718:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A catechisme in briefe questions and answers containing such things as are to be known or had by all such as would partake the sacrament of the Lords Supper with comfort / by John Geree ...</title>
                  <author>Geree, John, 1601?-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.C. for F. Grove and are to bee sold by Christopher Meredith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through, and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Catechisms.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109900:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>CATECHISME</hi> In briefe QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS, Containing ſuch things as are to be known or had by all ſuch as would partake the Sacrament of the <hi>LORDS S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PPER</hi> with comfort.</p>
            <p>By JOHN GEREE ſometime Miniſter of the Word in
<hi>Tewxbury,</hi> now Paſtor of St. <hi>Faiths</hi> under <hi>Pauls, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R.C.</hi> for <hi>F. Grove,</hi> and are to bee ſold by <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the Crane in Pauls church-yard, 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:109900:2"/>
            <p>Thoſe that want time or memory to learne the whole Catechiſme may firſt learn the more neceſſary anſwers marked in the Margent thus †† and only read and marke the reſt. For their direction.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109900:2"/>
            <p>Queſtion. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>OE you purpoſe to come to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.24.</note> Yes, leſt I ſhould diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Chriſt, and deprive my ſoule of benefit.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doe all receive benefit which come to the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.27. &amp; 17.</note> No: ſome are better, ſome are worſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who are better?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 30.3,18,19.</note> Such as come with due preparation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who come preparedly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28.</note> Such only as by examination find in themſelves ſome competent meaſure of knowledg, appetite, repentance, faith, love and reſolution to keepe the covenant which in this Sacrament they renew with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is knowledge neceſſary to worthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.28,29.</note> Becauſe examination is neceſſary, which cannot be without knowledg, nor without it can we diſcerne the Lords bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſo ſhal prophane this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt a man know?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> He ſhould know the grounds of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian<pb facs="tcp:109900:3"/>religion in generall, but eſpecially himſelfe, God and the nature of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why muſt a man know the grounds of Chriſtian religion in generall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.18. Hoſ. 4.6.</note> Becauſe no man ſhould be ignorant of the myſteries of his calling, much leſſe a Chriſtian, nor can a man know any one principle as he ſhould doe without ſome generall knowledge of all.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt he know concerning himſelfe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> What perfection he had by creation, what miſery by corruption, what benefit by renovation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What was our perfection by creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1.26,27.</note> We were created after Gods image which conſiſts in knowledge and holines.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is our miſery by corruption?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.24. Col. 3.10. Rom. 5.12. Eph.
1.2,2,3.</note> We are guilty of Adams ſinne, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the image of God, prone to all ſin, flaves of Satan, children of wrath, that is, lyable to Gods Iudgements here, death &amp; hell hereafter.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What benefit have we by renovation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11. Cor. 3 10. Rom. 8.15,16,17.</note> The guilt of our ſinnes is purged by the blood of Chriſt, we have in part the Image of God renewed upon us in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and holines, and have our right to heaven reſtored.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109900:3"/>Q. <hi>Why is this knowledg of himſelf neceſſary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.28. Mar. 9.12.</note> Becauſe til he know his miſery in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and the helpe he may have by Chriſt, he wil neither care for Chriſt nor this ſacrament nor any other meanes that conveys Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt he know concerning God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 34.6.7. 1 Ioh. 5.7.</note> The excellency and glory of the Deity in his eſſence and attributes, the myſtery of the Perſons, three in one eſſence, and one eſſence whole in three Perſons.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why muſt a man have this knowledg of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.6. Ioh. 1.14.</note> Unleſſe he know him in his eſſence hee will not care for this or any part of his worſhip, unleſſe he know the Trinitie in Unitie he cannot know Chriſt who is the authour and matter of this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17.10.11. Exod. 12.13.</note> An ordinance of God wherein by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſignes our faith is confirmed in the covenant of God, and ſome ſpeciall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thereof which are there repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and exhibited.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the covenant of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17.1,2. Exod. 19.5,6,7,8.</note> A compact between God and man wherein God requires ſome ſervice and promiſeth ſome reward, man promiſeth obedience and expecteth ſome reward.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many covenants hath God made with his Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109900:4"/>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> Two: the firſt of workes given to Adam in Paradiſe, the other of grace made with Adam after his fall and continued to us though diverſly in reſpect of the externall manifeſtation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the covenant of grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">5.31. Ioh. 3.16. Act. 2.38. &amp; 16.31. 1 Pet.
1.14.15.</note> A compact between God and the elect, wherein God freely promiſeth to them pardon of ſinne and power againſt it and ſalvation in Chriſt, and requires from them repentance, faith &amp; new obedience.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the difference between the covenant of grace and the other of workes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 26.25,26,27. Act. 5.31.</note> They differ two wayes, the one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires perfect obedience as the condition, the other onely repentance, faith and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere obedience: the one requires the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be done by our owne ſtrength, but in the covenant of grace though God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a condition he workes it in us.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many Sacraments are there annexed to the Goſpel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two: baptiſme and the Lords ſupper.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth it appeare there bee but two Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.26.28.19.</note> Chriſt hath ordained no more, given commiſſion to his Miniſters to adminiſter no more, wee need no more then to have entrance and growth in Chriſt ſignified.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109900:4"/>Q. <hi>What is the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.23 24,25,26.</note> It is a Sacrament of the renewed cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ordained of Chriſt, wherein by the uſe of bread and wine rightly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred and received, Chriſt Ieſus and all his benefits is ſignified, ſealed, and exhibited unto us, and his paſſion is gratefully commemorated by us.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who is the authour of this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.26.</note> Chriſt Ieſus, who inſtituted it at his laſt ſupper.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who is Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.6,7.</note> In perſon God &amp; man, in office our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour &amp; redeemer. 1 Tim. 3.16. Col. 1.14.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did Chriſt ordaine this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 1.21. 1 Cor. 11.24,26. Mat. 6 35. 1 Cor.
10.17.</note> Firſt, to continue the memory of his death. 2 To manifeſt and exhibite the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of refreſhing that is in Chriſt. 3 To comfort us after temptation by renewing our covenant. 4 to ſtrengthen our faith, to ſignifie and increaſe mutuall love &amp; unity.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What is the matter of this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.26.27.27.</note> Twofold: inward, which is Chriſt and his benefits; outward, to wit the ſignes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What be the ſignes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Twofold: elementall and rituall, the one ſignifying Chriſt, the other the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What be the elementall ſignes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109900:5"/>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.26,27,28.</note> Bread and wine, the one ſignifying the body, the other the bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What be the rituall ſignes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.24. Mat. 26.28.</note> Rites or actions, as the breaking of the bread ſignifying the ſufferings of Chriſt, the powring out of the wine that his bloud was ſhed, the miniſter giving the elements ſignifies God the Father giving Chriſt, the peoples taking the elements, ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their receiving Chriſt by faith.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What union is there between the ſignes and the thing ſignified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.34. Acts 3.21.</note> Not viſible or locall, but myſticall and ſpirituall, yet true and reall.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doe we partake of them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.26,27.</note> The ſignes wee partake corporally, the thing ſignified ſpiritually according to their proper natures.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>how can we partake of Chriſt &amp; he in heaven</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A. By having a right and title given to us, as we receive land by evidences, not as we take medicine in a box.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What difference is there between Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall and common bread?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.26.</note> None in nature, only in uſe, this being ſet apart for holy uſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How have theſe elements this holy relation to ſeale and repreſent ſpirituall things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.23,24,25. 1 Cor. 10.16.</note> By being conſecrated to this holy uſe:<pb facs="tcp:109900:5"/>w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> conſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſiſts partly in Chriſts firſt inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch elements for ſuch uſe, partly in the miniſters declaring <hi>Chriſts</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, bleſſing <hi>God</hi> for our redemtion &amp; theſe ſeals of it, praying to him for to bleſs the elements for the preſent to that holy uſe, to which himſelf hath ordained them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſecond thing neceſſary in a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy communicant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Spirituall Appetite. Eſa. 55.1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is ſuch an appetite neceſſary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.37. Rev. 22.15.</note> Becauſe this Sacrament is a ſpirituall feaſt; and our invitation and welcome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why muſt we deſire it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not for cuſtom or company but in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God, &amp; the benefit of our ſouls.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall a man know he hath a deſire?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Deſire is the inclination of our hearts after a thing which is of it ſelfe diſcerna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to us.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>how ſhal we know the ſincerity of our deſires?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the grounds which in our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we finde do move us to it and by our conſtancy of communicating at all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, not at ſolemne feaſts only.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may deſire be ſtirred in us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A.
<note place="margin">Mat. 9.12. Pſal. 63.1,2,3.</note> By due conſideration of our own neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and the Sacraments vertue, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation<pb facs="tcp:109900:6"/>of Chriſts command.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the third thing requiſite in a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy communicant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> Iuſtifying faith: a man muſt bring his evidence that hath any good by the ſcale.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.8. Phil. 3.9.</note> Faith is a ſaving grace whereby we goe out of our ſelves, and reſt upon Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone for ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is faith neceſſary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.6. Ioh. 4.10. Ioh. 1.12 Eph.
3.17.</note> Faith is neceſſary to the acceptable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of every part of Gods worſhip, its the ground of true deſire after the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, its the mouth &amp; hand of the ſoule to receive Chriſt offerd in the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>How ſhal a man know whether he hath faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.17. Pſal. 116.10. 2 Iam. 17. 1 Pet.
22.</note> Firſt, by the nature of faith. 2 By the means whereby true faith is wrought, for faith is wrought by the word and ſpirit. 3 By the fruits, which are prayer, love to the word, obedience &amp; dependance on
<hi>God</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How will a man get faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 28.16. Rom. 10.17. Mat. 9.24.</note> By hearing the word and ſeeking it at Gods hand.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the</hi> 4. <hi>thing in worthy receiving?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Repentance.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is repentance neceſſary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 5.31. Tit. 1.15. Hag. 2.15.14. Num. 6.67. &amp;c. Ier. 4.1. Ioel. 1.12. Lam. 3.40. Iam. 4.9. Zach. 12.10. Ier.
31.18,19.</note> Becauſe we come to have pardon of ſinne ſealed to us which preſuppoſeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;<pb facs="tcp:109900:6"/>and if the conſcience be defiled with any knowne ſinne, it defiles our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices: none might come to the Paſſeover which were not legally cleane.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 20.43. Hoſ. 14.3.</note> It is a work of grace whereby a man convict of ſin doth humble his ſoule with godly ſorrow and holy ſhame for it, and reſolve againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What particulars are required therein?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31. Ezek. 36.32. Prov. 28.13. Pſal.
51.17. Ier. 7.5.</note> Firſt examination to find out ſinne. 2 Affection to mourne for it and to judge our ſelves and to hate it &amp; to be aſhamed of it. 3 Confeſſion. 4 An hearty deſire of pardon. 5 Reſolution againſt ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How may we find out ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.7. &amp; 3.20. Iam. 1.23.25.</note> By comparing our ſelves to the law of God w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſhould be the rule of our actions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. how ſhal we know whether we have repented</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.11. 1 Cor. 6.11.</note> It works an univerſall change, it makes us of fooliſh wiſe, of carnall ſpirituall, of prophane holy in all our converſations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How ſhall we get repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A.
<note place="margin">Act. 5.31. &amp; 2.3.7.2 Tim. 2.5.</note> We muſt ſeek it of Chriſt, whoſe office it is to give it, and in the word, by which as an inſtrument it is wrought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What may further helpe to breake our hearts for ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.16,17,18,19. Pſal. 7.11. Epheſ. 5.6. Iſa. 5.3. to the end Iſa. 55.6,7. Ier. 3.12.</note> The conſideration of Gods infinite<pb facs="tcp:109900:7"/>wrath againſt ſinne, manifeſted in the puniſhment of Adam and his poſteritie, all the judgements of this life and hel hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the puniſhment he laid on Chriſt, as alſo thought of his mercy in pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſinne if we repent.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the</hi> 5. <hi>thing in worthy receiving?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.18.</note> Love and peace with our neighbours.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is love neceſſary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.17 Mat. 5.23,24. 1 Tim. 2.8.</note> God here ſeales his love to us, and ſeals our union one with another, it is a love-feaſt: beſides no ſervice is accepted which is not done in love.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What it love?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.22. 1 Cor. 13. Gal. 6.10.</note> A gratious affection of the heart, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we wiſh and endevour good to all, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to the godly.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall we know whether we have love?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.4,5,6,7. Rom. 12.15. 1 Peter. 4.8. Gal. 5.22.</note> By the fruits, ſuch are ſympathy, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring infirmities, forgiving injuries.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall we attaine this love?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By prayer, for it is a fruit of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt we doe if there be any breach of love between us and others?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.23,24.</note> Seek reconciliation, and not omit the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What if reconciliation cannot be had?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28.</note> If it be truly ſought for on our part we are ſafe, it is our owne not others malice<pb facs="tcp:109900:7"/>which makes us unfit for the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What if they have provoked us and made no ſatisfaction?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.12,13.</note> Yet we muſt forgive and not deſire re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, Chriſt muſt be our rule who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave us freely.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the laſt thing neceſſary in prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> A purpoſe to keep that covenant which we made in Baptiſme, and now renew in the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhy is this neceſſary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2 17.</note> Becauſe without this a man mocks <hi>God,</hi> making ſhew of covenanting wth him but thinks of nothing leſſe, &amp; this purpoſe of new obedience is a neceſſary fruit of faith.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may we know whether we have this purpoſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Our conſciences are the only witneſſes in this: when we make a covenant with a man we know whether we mean to keepe it; ſo may we in our covenant with God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat helpes may we have in attaining this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.12. Mat. 25.34.</note> We muſt conſider if our purpoſes be ſincere Chriſt will helpe us to keepe them, accept ſincere though weake ſervice, and give us an ineſtimable reward, ſo it will be the beſt bargaine that can be made.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat if we find not this qualification?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109900:8"/>A. If we have it not in ſome meaſure, we muſt ſeeke it before we preſume to come to the Lords Table, there be degrees in it, the more preparation the more fruit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the danger of unworthy receiving?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28,29.</note> Very great, for inſtead of having bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by Chriſts bloud, we are guilty of it, and make our ſelves liable to temporall and eternall judgments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is it not beſt then to omit this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A.
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.3.7. Heb. 10.25.</note> No, abſenting from the Sacrament is no better, nor ſafer then the profaning of it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt we then doe if we find want of preparation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.6. 2 Cor. 8.12. 2 Chron. 30.19.</note> Lament our wants, &amp; deſire &amp; endevour after theſe graces, and we ſhal be accepted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. If we have once been prepared, may we be afterwards ſecure?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No, we muſt prepare anew: for there are required not only the habits of theſe graces, but renewed acts of them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ends are we to aime at in receiving the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Chiefly two.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.30.31. 1 Cor. 11.24,25,26. 2 Cor.
5.14.15.</note> The honouring of Chriſt by a grateful commemoration of his death.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When doe we commemorate the death of Chriſt gratefully?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109900:8"/>A. When we ponder his love &amp; goodneſſe ſhining in it, and have our hearts enlarged with love, joy, &amp; thankfulnes for it, feeling an holy conſtraint from it, to live to him &amp; to ſuffer, yea to die for him if need require.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the ſecond end to be aimed at in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">2 Cor 10.16.</note> To benefit our ſouls by being further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in fuller application and participation of the merit and vertue of Chriſt which God doth in this ordinance offer and ſeal to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What demeanour is required of us in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A. Such reverence as becomes the Table of ſo great a God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A. We muſt have our minds ſet on worke by the ſignes to meditate on the thing ſignified, and with joy remember the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt and apply them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What muſt we doe after participation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A. We muſt give extraordinary thankes to God for vouchſafing us to be his gueſts at his Table, and there refreſhing our ſouls with the vertue and merit of his bleſſed Son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is to be done elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>A. We muſt remember our covenant with <pb facs="tcp:109900:9"/>God and ſtrive to keep it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> We muſt examine and conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we profit by the Sacrament or not.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What if a man be worſe after it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.32.</note> If he be ſo indeed, then he hath eaten unworthily and muſt be humbled.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What if we finde benefit by the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">††</note>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.33,35.</note> We muſt be very thankfull and greatly rejoyce, for Chriſt is the bread of life, hee that once eateth of Chriſt ſpiritually ſhal be ſure to be nouriſhed to eternall life; hee may be ſicke in his ſoule, but he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver die.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
